((バチ
B
o
y
s
'
I
n
t
e
r
h
i
g
h
V
o
l
e
y
b
a
l
T
o
u
r
n
a
m
e
n
t
P
r
e
l
i
m
n
a
r
i
e
s
B
r
a
c
k
e
t
Episode Twenty-five:
The Third Day
Shiratorizawa!
Unstoppable Force
(白鳥沢応援団)しらとりざわ
ココンコンココン
(青城応援団)行け
行け行け行け行け青城
Go, go, go, go, Seijou!
Rule the Court
(部員)押せ
押せ押せ押せ押せ青城
Attack! Attack, attack, attack, attack, Seijou!
(青城応援団)押せ
押せ押せ押せ押せ青城
Shiratorizawa!
(及川)今日こそ
へこましてやるから覚悟しなよ
Get ready, because this is the day
I humiliate you, my dear little Ushiwaka.
ウシワカちゃん
(牛島)その呼び方やめろ及川
Don't call me that, Oikawa.
Aoba Jousai               Shiratorizawa
(拍手)
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]ｷｰﾝｺｰﾝｶｰﾝｺｰﾝ(ﾁｬｲﾑ)
(生徒)腹減た
(生徒)購買行こうぜ
I'm starving!
Let's hit the school shop.
日向飯食おうぜ
Hinata, let's eat.
あそういや
昨日惜しかたんだてな
Right. Come to think of it,
I heard you came close yesterday.
うちも先週
３回戦で負けちゃてさぁ
Our team also lost in the third round last week.
結局俺たちに勝た相手が
全国にん
The guys who beat us ended up going to nationals.
どうした食わねぇの
便所
What's wrong? Aren't you hungry?
Bathroom.
(田中)日向と影山が
初めてバレ部に来た日
The very first day Hinata and Kageyama came to practice,
大地さんは
｢春高｣に行くて言た
Daichi said we'd go to spring nationals.
(西谷)春高
一次予選は８月だけか
I forget, is the first qualifying round for that in August?
(田中)俺たちで
もう一回行くて言た
He said we'd be going there one more time.
敗戦に浸てる余裕ねぇよ
There's no time to wallow in defeat.
(澤村)俺はここで退いた方が
いいと思ている
I'm thinking now would be a good time to retire.
(澤村)春高に
３年が出られるようになて
Ever since third-years could take part in the spring tournament,
絶対そこまで残て
I've wanted us to survive the elimination and go to Tokyo to play in it.
東京行て戦てやるて
思てた
But seeing the first and second-years in action
１２年見てたら少しでも早く
got me thinking it would be better to surrender the team to them sooner than later.
あいつらに部を明け渡した方が
いいんじゃないかて思た
(澤村)
将来有望なあいつらメインの
It would be better for the team to have it restructured around them,
新体制チムで
スタトした方が
the guys who show such promise—
Daichi, is that what you really want?
(菅原)確かに大地は
主将ていう重い立場だけど
I know that being captain puts you in a position of responsibility,
自分を完全に殺す必要
ないんじゃねぇの
but I don't think you need to remove yourself entirely.
前からそう決めてたんなら
何も言わないけど
If that was always your plan, I won't complain.
Otherwise, you should play it out the way you want to.
そうじゃないなら最後くらい
もとやりたいようにやんなよ
ふぅ
俺は言たとおり居残る
I'm staying on, just as I said I would!
１２年に出ていてくださいて
言われたらそんとき考える
I'll only consider leaving if and when
the younger members ask me to leave!
大地と旭がいなくてもな
With or without you two!
But I told you I was staying on yesterday!
(東峰)俺は
昨日残るて言たべよ
もともと進学希望じゃないし
I'm not going to college anyway.
１２年に出ていてくださいて
言われたらへこむ
If the younger members asked me to leave, I'd take it hard.
I...
(澤村)俺は
(２人)ん
(澤村)
俺だてまだやりてぇよ
I still want to play too, you know!
お前らとまだバレしてぇ
I still want to play volleyball with you guys!
≪(先生)武田先生
(武田)ん
Mr. Takeda?
バレ部のことで
ちょといいですか
Might we have a word regarding the volleyball team?
Sure.
(嶋田)((試合出られたな
So you got to play in a match, huh?
どうだた
How'd you like it?
楽しかたか忠))
Did you have fun, Tadashi?
(山口)((いいえ
No.
((いいえ
No!
(嶋田)((だろうな
I thought so.
自分の思うように体が動かない
ボルは飛ばない
You tense up and can't move the way you want to.
The ball won't fly right.
楽しいわけねぇよな))
There's nothing fun about that.
((中学まではみんなで
わいわいやるのが楽しいて
Up until junior high, I played volleyball thinking it was a fun sort of thing to do with my friends.
漠然と思てました
That's all it was to me.
それが
俺にとてのバレでした
でもそういうんじゃない
そういうんじゃなくて
But it's nothing like that.
It's different.
俺もあいつらみたいに
I can't do what they do.
I want full control of my body!
(山口)((自分の体を操りたい
ボルを操りたい
I want to control the ball!
I want to play as equals against good players!
強いヤツらと対等に戦いたい
((勝負事で本当に楽しむためには
強さがいる))
"To truly enjoy playing sports, you need to be strong."
(嶋田)
((烏養監督じいさんの方な))
Coach Ukai...
The older one, I mean.
((監督に昔よく言われた))
That's what he used to say to me.
((俺はもちろん
エスじゃなかたし
Needless to say, I wasn't the ace, and I wasn't a starter.
スタメンでもなかた))
((練習もきついし
やめたいと思たこともあた
Practicing was hard, and there were times I felt like quitting.
But...
(嶋田)((初めて試合で
ｻｰﾋﾞｽｴｰｽを決めたとき思たよ
When I nailed a service ace for the first time in a real match, it finally clicked.
ああ俺はこの一本のために
Hey, this is the play I've practiced so long for.
何十時間も練習したんだ
そんでこの一試合この一本
この瞬間をまた味わえるなら
That's when I decided that I would buckle down and practice hard,
just to experience this one match, point, and moment all over again.
きつい練習もやれるて思たよ))
((よしゃやるか
Okay, let's get started!
(嶋田)((次の試合までだて
時間足んねぇからな))
There isn't much time until the next match.
ツキご飯食べよう
(月島)山口うるさい
Tsukki, let's eat!
Yamaguchi, you're annoying.
ふふごめんツキ
Sorry, Tsukki!
Tsukki!
Faculty Office
菅原と澤村は
進学クラスなのに
Both Sugawara and Sawamura gave me advance notice
前々からインタハイ終わても
部活を続けると言てまして
they would be staying on the team past the interhigh despite their plans to go to college.
特に菅原は
And in Sugawara's case...
(菅原)((失礼します))
Excuse me.
(先生)((菅原))
Sugawara.
I understand how you feel,
but you really should focus on your studies.
((気持ちは分かるが
勉強に専念した方がいい
正直部活を続けてお前に
メリトがあるとは思えない))
I honestly don't think you have anything to gain by staying on the team.
((先生俺
I don't play volleyball because there's something to gain, sir.
メリトがあるから
バレやてるんじゃないんです))
Sugawara isn't in the starting lineup for matches, is that correct?
菅原は試合でのﾚｷﾞｭﾗｰﾒﾝﾊﾞｰでは
ないんですよね
(武田)えええ
スポツ推薦の見込みも薄い
Y-Yes.
He doesn't have much hope for a sports scholarship either.
二人とも日頃の成績は
優秀ではありますが
Both boys get excellent grades, but the question is can they maintain those grades?
それを維持できるかどうか
３年生と
話をしてもらえますか
Would you please speak to the third-years?
くれぐれも
いときの感情ではなく
Be sure to address their futures rather than their current emotional state.
先を見据えた話を
大人の言葉が彼らの言い訳に
なてはいけませんから
Don't let them use what an adult told them as an excuse.
(滝ノ上)んあいつら
(繋心)どうした
I bet...
What's up?
(滝ノ上)
やぱへこんでんだろうな
I'll bet they're feeling lousy.
今日は朝練も午後も休みにした
I gave them the morning and afternoon off.
It hasn't even been a day yet.
昨日の今日じゃな
強かたな青葉城西
Aoba Jousai sure was tough.
強かたすげぇ強かた
They were tough. Really tough.
今回俺たちは
いい勝負できたけど
We played well this time around,
次また戦たとき
今回と同じくらい
but who knows if we'll put up that good of a fight the next time we play them.
善戦できるかは分かんねぇ
でも青城は同じだけの強さを
安定して発揮してくるんだろう
Seijou will undoubtedly come at us again with the same consistent force.
向こうのﾀｲﾑｱｳﾄ中の様子見たか
ああ
Did you see them during their timeouts?
Yeah.
ほとんど選手だけで
ミティングが成立してた
It was mainly player-only meetings.
監督たちは
後ろから様子を見守て
Their coaches kept watch from the background.
I'm sure they offered a few helpful words, of course.
そりゃ助言はするだろうけどさ
選手が常に考えて試合の中で
臨機応変に対応していく
Their players are always thinking and adapting to every situation within the match.
こちがどんな飛び道具を
持ち出しても
No matter what projectile weapon we bring out, they always combat it, calm and efficient.
冷静に素早く攻略される
Whatever we did, they just refused to fall apart.
なのに向こうは
なかなか崩れてくれねぇ
It was really stressful.
ストレスがたまるんだよな
でも
The only team capable of prying the points away from a carefully orchestrated powerhouse like Seijou...
青城の練り上げられた強さを
前にしても
力ずくで点を奪ていく
(繋心)それが白鳥沢なんだろう
has to be Shiratorizawa.
Unstoppable Force
≪今までの
練習とか経験とか策略とか
All the practicing and strategizing we've done,
and the experience we have,
全部力だけでへし折ていく≫
is being torn apart by sheer brute force.
(及川)まあ勝利までの過程なんて
関係ないよね
Not like it matters how you win, really.
コトに
ボルを落とした方が負け
Whoever lets the ball touch the ground loses.
それが全て
That's all that matters.
Haikyuu !!
(武田)
もし君たちが無理をすれば
If you were afflicted with an injury that could
jeopardize your future if it wasn't allowed to heal,
将来にも影響してしまうような
ケガを抱えていて
yet you still wanted to play for the only reason that
you could never play again, I would have to stop you.
それでも今しかないからと
試合に出ようとしたならば
僕はきと止める
Certain things must never be acted upon during an emotional time.
いときの感情で
動くべきでないこともある
ただ
何度でも挑戦できることならば
But if it's something you can challenge yourselves to do many times, I believe that gives you options.
選択肢はあると
僕は思ています
Obviously, the possibility of failing
your exams is not to be taken lightly.
もちろん試験に落ちることが
どうてことないなんて
言いません
難関を越えていくには
Overcoming obstacles requires the
appropriate effort, patience, and sacrifice.
相応の努力や我慢
犠牲が必要です
君たちが部活に費やす時間も
ほかの子らは
The time you spend on your extracurricular activities
is time that the other students will spend studying and working for the future.
勉強や将来確実に
ためになることに費やしていて
そこには当然差が生まれる
This will most definitely create a disparity.
その差に君たちは
大きく後悔するかもしれない
One day, you may regret that disparity deeply.
考えて選んでください
Please think it over and choose.
君たちが
５年後１０年後に後悔しない方を
Choose the option you won't regret five or ten years from now.
腰高ぇよ
うん
Squat lower.
Right.
決勝の決着つく頃だな
The finals will be wrapping up by now.
Yeah.
勝た方が全国に進むんだな
The winners advance to nationals.
いぱい試合すんだな
The winners get to play lots of matches.
Yeah.
くそたらぁ
Goddammit!
ぐ
ぐおふんくぅ
Shit.
くそ
あああ
くそがぁ
You shit!
うおお
うわぁ
勝ちてぇ
I wanna win.
俺はもう謝んねぇ
I will never apologize again.
謝んなきゃいけないようなトスは
I will never make a set I need to apologize for...
上げねぇ
ever again!
コトに残るのは
Only the strong...
強いヤツだけ
...get to stay on the court.
時間ない
There's no time.
止まてる暇ない
There's no time to stand still!
(清水)
でもお昼はちゃんと食べなさい
But you have to eat your lunch.
あきさ
Uh...
清水先輩
Shimizu?!
を発しないように
And try not to scream so much.
I heard you all the way from the clubroom.
部室まで聞こえた
ハフィ
Y-You...
≪(田中･西谷)潔子さん
(３人)ん
Kiyoko!
(田中)
潔子さん今日も美しいす
Kiyoko, you look lovely today.
I crossed the seven seas to come see you!
(西谷)あなたに会いに来ました
We'll faithfully follow you for life!
(２人)
あなたに一生ついていきます
≫ドン
はぁ
(縁下)ケガすんなよ
先輩たち今日休みじゃ
Don't hurt yourselves.
Aren't we supposed to have today off?
ははじゃあなんで
お前らはここにいるんだ
Then explain what you guys are doing here.
Afternoon!
≪(山口)ちわす
(一同)ん
Hello.
(西谷)あとは３年か
Now all we need are the third-years.
(縁下)でも
今日はもともと部活ないし
But we didn't even have practice scheduled for today.
Hey, hey, hey!
(田中)おいおいおい３年が
引退なんかするわけねぇだろ
You know the third-years would never retire!
えどういうことですか
３年
Huh? What do you mean?
No way.
３年生は
３年生は残りますよね
The third-years are staying on the team, right?!
They're taking part in the spring tournament, aren't they?!
春高に行くて言たの
変わらないですよね
あ
(菅原)ヤバいヤバい早く
Crap. Hurry!
That's right.
変わらない
うぅ
They still are.
(田中)遅いすよ
(菅原)ふぅ
You're late!
Let's go to spring nationals!
行くぞ春高
(一同)よしゃ
All right!
(繋心)≪つい来ちまたけど
Here I am, at the school.
誰か物好きなヤツ来てかな≫
I wonder if any crazy bastards have shown up?
ん
(田中)せい
(一同)ナイスキ
Nice spike!
≫ガラガラガラ
あ
(一同)はざす
Afternoon, sir!
お前ら元気じゃねぇかん
Why, you guys are doing fine.
(澤村)改めて
ご指導よろしくお願いします
Please coach us once again!
Thank you!
(一同)お願いします
(繋心)俺たちは
優劣を決める試合で負けた
We lost in a match to determine the superior team.
青城は強かた
俺たちはそれに劣た
Seijou was tough.
We were inferior to them.
That's the current result—the reality.
それが現時点での結果で事実だ
(繋心)
で今日のインタハイ決勝
So, the winner of today's interhigh prelims final...
優勝は
was...
(繋心)白鳥沢だ
Shiratorizawa.
Shiratorizawa                Aoba Jousai
Seijou...
青城が
負けた
...lost?
県内でさえ
あの青城より上がいる
There's a team that beats Seijou within our own prefecture.
強くなるしかねぇ
We have to be stronger.
I'm sure you already know our next objective.
次の目標は
もう分かてると思うが
春高だ
出場する３年にとては
Spring nationals.
Obviously, this will be the final match for the third-years.
文字どおり最後の戦いになる
≪春高
小さな巨人の行た舞台≫
Spring nationals.
The place where the Little Giant went!
(繋心)じゃあ
とりあえずここは主将に
Okay, now let's have a word of motivation from your captain.
一発気合い入れてもらおうか
(澤村)あ
(澤村)
昔烏野が一度だけ行た舞台
It's the venue Karasuno has only been to once.
東京オレンジコトだ
The Orange Court in Tokyo!
もう一度あそこへ行く
And we're going there once again!
(一同)よしゃ
All right!
(繋心)休憩
(一同)おす
Take five!
Yessir!
影山
ん
Kageyama.
次こそ絶対に勝つぞ
We're going to win this time.
俺たちでみんなで
You and me and all of us!
Right.
(繋心)よし休憩終わり
(２人)おす
Okay, break time's over!
Yessir!
(ﾅﾚｰｼｮﾝ)＜目の前に立ちはだかる
高い高い壁＞
A massive, massive wall stands
in front of me, blocking my way.
(繋心)スパイク練習行くぞ
(一同)おす
Time for spike practice!
Yessir!
行くぞ
Here goes!
The view on the other side is something I'll never be able to see alone.
＜その向こうは俺独りでは
決して見ることのできない＞
次日向
お願いしゃす
Next! Hinata!
I'm ready!
持てこい
Send it my way!
＜それが
That's the view from the summit.
頂の景色＞
We run laps convinced that we will all make it
We suffer through the nights for a vision we chose on a whim
If you really want fairness then we'd all look basically the same
We will suffer through more nights for a vision instead of standing still
Our passion burns until the morning and we advance with closed eyes
I haven't forgotten you despite this passion
I run with only my headlight for guidance
No matter what awaits me I will laugh in this body I was born in
Is there someone running with your taillight for guidance?
What you call determination just means bunching up
Is someone going to follow up on all these impressions?
Will vowing to never falter let me laugh again?
Fly